by software and robots in the next 20 years.
ببرامج محوسبه و أجهزة آلية في غضون 20 سنة مقبلة
And many corporate leaders welcome that as a chance to increase profits.
و كثير من مديري الشركات يرحبون بهذه الفكره كوسيلة لزيادة الأرباح
Machines are more efficient;
الآلات الرقمية أكثر إنتاجاً
humans are complicated and difficult to manage.
البشر معقدون و من الصعب إدارتهم
Well, I want our organizations to remain human.
حسنا سأقولها ،أريد لمنظماتنا أن تظل بشرية
In fact, I want them to become beautiful.
في الحقيقه ،أريدهم أن يكونوا جميلين
Because as machines take our jobs and do them more efficiently,
لأنه بمجرد ان تاخذ الالات مكان البشر و تنتج لكبار المستثمرين انتاجا اكثر
soon the only work left for us humans will be the kind of work
سوف يصبح العمل الذي يقوم به البشر قريبا
that must be done beautifully rather than efficiently.
يُنجز بشكل جميل عوضاً من الإتقان
To maintain our humanity in the this second Machine Age,
لكي نحافظ على إنسانيتنا في عالم الآلي
we may have no other choice than to create beauty.
لا يوجد لدينا خيار آخر غير أن نصنع الجمال
Beauty is an elusive concept.
الجمال مفهوم خاص
For the writer Stendhal it was the promise of happiness.
بالنسبه للكاتب ستندهال . الجمال هو مضمون السعادة
For me it's a goal by Lionel Messi.
بالنسبه لي هو هدف من أهداف ليونيل ميسي.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So bear with me
لذلك تأملوا معي
as I am proposing four admittedly very subjective principles
و انا أقترح أربعة مبادىء
that you can use to build a beautiful organization.
يمكن أن تُستعمل لكي تبني مؤسسات جميلة
First: do the unnecessary.
أولاً: افعلوا ما ليس ضرورياً
[Do the Unnecessary]
[ افعلوا ما ليس ضروريا ]
A few months ago, Hamdi Ulukaya,
قبل عدة أشهر
the CEO and founder of the yogurt company Chobani,
المدير التنفيذي و مؤسس شركة كوباني لتصنيع الزبادي
made headlines when he decided to grant stock to all of his 2,000 employees.
تصدر العناوين عندما قرر أن يوزع حصص مساهمة لكل من 2000 موظف في المؤسسة
Some called it a PR stunt,
البعض ظن إنها خدعة تجارية
others -- a genuine act of giving back.
آخرون قالوا بإنها نوع من إرجاع المعروف
But there is something else that was remarkable about it.
و لكن كان هناك شئ آخر مميز بخصوصها
It came completely out of the blue.
و قد أتى فجأة
There had been no market or stakeholder pressure,
لم يكن هناك ضغط من سوق أو مستثمرين
and employees were so surprised
و قد تفاجأ الموظفون
that they burst into tears when they heard the news.
لدرجه أنهم ذرفوا دموعأ عندما سمعوا بالخبر
Actions like Ulukaya's are beautiful because they catch us off guard.
أفعال مثل أفعال المدير التنفيذي (لوكايا) تفاجئنا لأنها جميلة
They create something out of nothing
و تخلق شئ من العدم
because they're completely unnecessary.
لأنها ليست مطلوبة
I once worked at a company
عملت مرة في شركة
that was the result of a merger
كانت نتيجه لدمج شركات متعددة
of a large IT outsourcing firm and a small design firm.
مكونة من شركة معلومات كبيرة و شركة تصميم صغيرة
We were merging 9,000 software engineers
كنا قد تم جمعنا لنكون 9000 مهندس برمجيات
with 1,000 creative types.
بعدد 1000 نوع متخصص
And to unify these immensely different cultures,
و لكي يتم توحيد هذه الثقافات المختلفه
we were going to launch a third, new brand.
كنا بصدد إطلاق منتج جديد
And the new brand color was going to be orange.
و لون المنتج الجديد برتقالي
And as we were going through the budget for the rollouts,
و أثناء مراجعتنا للميزانيه للتخلص من الفائض الغير ضروري
we decided last minute
في آخر دقيقه قررنا
to cut the purchase of 10,000 orange balloons,
أن نلغي شراء 10000 بالونه برتقالية
which we had meant to distribute to all staff worldwide.
كنا سوف نقوم لتوزيعها لموظفينا في أنحاء العالم
They just seemed unnecessary and cute in the end.
اعتقدنا انها غير ضروريه و لطيفة, في النهايه
I didn't know back then
لم أكن اعلم في ذلك الوقت
that our decision marked the beginning of the end --
أن قرارنا رسم بدايه النهاية
that these two organizations would never become one.
ان هاتان المنظمتان لن تكونا موحدتان
And sure enough, the merger eventually failed.
و بالتالي بالطبع، فشل الدمج
Now, was it because there weren't any orange balloons?
لننظر للأمر الآن، هل كان الفشل بسبب عدم وجود البالونات ؟
No, of course not.
قطعا لا
But the kill-the-orange-balloons mentality permeated everything else.
لكن قرار إلغاء توزيع البالونات جهز الشركة للانهيار
You might not always realize it, but when you cut the unnecessary,
ربما لا تدرك ذلك دائما ، لكن عندما تستغني عن الغير ضروري
you cut everything.
تستغني عن كل شئ
Leading with beauty means rising above what is merely necessary.
القياده الرائعه تعني الارتقاء فوق ما هو بالكاد ضروري
So do not kill your orange balloons.
لكي لا تفقع بالوناتك البرتقاليه
The second principle:
المبدأ الثاني :
create intimacy.
أخلق الود
[Create Intimacy]
[ اخلق الود ]
Studies show that how we feel about our workplace
تُظهر نتائج الدراسات أن ما نشعر به بخصوص مكان عملنا
very much depends on the relationships with our coworkers.
يعتمد على علاقاتنا مع زملائنا في العمل
And what are relationships other than a string of microinteractions?
و ما العلاقات إلا تفاعلات بسيطة؟
There are hundreds of these every day in our organizations
هناك المئات منها في مؤسساتنا كل يوم
that have the potential to distinguish a good life from a beautiful one.
لديها القدرة على التفريق بين الحياة الجيدة و الجميلة
The marriage researcher John Gottman says
الباحث في الحياة الزوجيه جون غوتمان قال
that the secret of a healthy relationship
إن سر العلاقة الصحية الجيدة
is not the great gesture or the lofty promise,
ليس إظهار نيه حسنه أو وعد نبيل
it's small moments of attachment.
إنه في لحظات الاتصال
In other words, intimacy.
بكلمات أُخرى ، الود
In our networked organizations,
في علمنا علم مؤسسات الشبكة
we tout the strength of weak ties
تعلمنا أن القوة في الروابط الضعيفة
but we underestimate the strength of strong ones.
و لكننا نقلل من قوة الروابط القوية
We forget the words of the writer Richard Bach who once said,
ننسى كلمات الكاتب ريتشارد باخ الذي قال
"Intimacy --
"الود
not connectedness --
ليس الترابط
intimacy is the opposite of loneliness."
الود هو عكس الوحدة"
So how do we design for organizational intimacy?
إذاً كيف نصمم مؤسسات يوجد بها ود؟
The humanitarian organization CARE
المؤسسة المعنية بأمور البشرية
wanted to launch a campaign on gender equality
إرادة تُنشئ شركه قائمة على الوحدة بين الجنسين
in villages in northern India.
في قرية في شمال الهند
But it realized quickly
سرعان ما أدركوا
that it had to have this conversation first with its own staff.
أنهم من المفترض أن يتحدثوا مع موظفيهم
So it invited all 36 team members and their partners
لذلك قاموا بجمع كل 36 فرد من المجموعة و شركائهم
to one of the Khajuraho Temples,
لإحدى المعابد في كاجواره
known for their famous erotic sculptures.
المعروفون بتماثيلهم المشهورة
And there they openly discussed their personal relationships --
و هناك ناقشوا علاقاتهم الشخصيه على الملىء
their own experiences of gender equality
و تجربتهم بخصوص المساواة بين الجنسين
with the coworkers and the partners.
بين زملاء العمل و الشركاء
It was eye-opening for the participants.
و قد كان مفاجآت للمشاركين
Not only did it allow them to relate to the communities they serve,
لم يجعلهم فقط مرتبطين بالمجتمعات التي يخدمونها
it also broke down invisible barriers
بل و قد كسر الحواجز الغير مرئية
and created a lasting bond amongst themselves.
و خلق رابطة دائمة بينهم
Not a single team member quit in the next four years.
لم يستقل فرد واحد لمدة أربع سنوات
So this is how you create intimacy.
إذاً هذه هي الطريقة لخلق الود
No masks ...
من غير أقنعة
or lots of masks.
أو أقنعة كثيرة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
When Danone, the food company,
عندما (دانوا )، شركه الطعام
wanted to translate its new company manifesto into product initiatives,
أرادت تحويل بيان الشركة الرسمي لبداية منتج
it gathered the management team
قامت بجمع الفريق الإداري
and 100 employees from across different departments,
و 100موظف من أقسام مختلفة
seniority levels and regions
بناءاً على الخبره و المنطقه
for a three-day strategy retreat.
لمدة ثالثة أيام لإعادة التأهيل
And it asked everybody to wear costumes for the entire meeting:
وطلب من الموظفين ارتداء زي في كل فترة اللقاء
wigs, crazy hats, feather boas,
شعر مستعار ، قبعات غريبه ، شالات
huge glasses and so on.
نظارات كبيره و من هذا القبيل
And they left with concrete outcomes
و يخرجوا من الاجتماعات بنتائج مذهلة
and full of enthusiasm.
و بحماس عالي
And when I asked the woman who had designed this experience
و عندما سألت النسوة التي صممت هذه التجربة
why it worked,
لماذا نجحت التجربة
she simply said, "Never underestimate the power of a ridiculous wig."
قالت ببساطة لا تقلل من أهمية الشعر المستعار
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Because wigs erase hierarchy,
لأن الشعر المستعر يزيل الرتابة
and hierarchy kills intimacy --
و الرتابة تقتل الود
both ways,
في كلا الحالتين
for the CEO and the intern.
بالنسبة للمدير التنفيذي و المتدربين
Wigs allow us to use the disguise of the false
الشعر المستعار يسمح لنا باستخدام التخفي الخاطئ
to show something true about ourselves.
لكي يظهروا شئ حقيقي عنهم
And that's not easy in our everyday work lives,
و هذا ليس من السهل في نظام عملنا المعتاد
because the relationship with our organizations
لأن علاقاتنا بمؤسساتنا
is often like that of a married couple that has grown apart,
مثل زوجين تفرقا
suffered betrayals and disappointments,
عانوا من خيانات و إحباط
and is now desperate to be beautiful for one another once again.
و هم الآن يائسين ليكونوا سعداء مع بعضهم
And for either of us the first step towards beauty involves a huge risk.
و لكلانا الخطوة الأولى تجاه الجمال تتضمن مخاطرة كبيرة
The risk to be ugly.
خطورة البشاعة
[Be Ugly]
البشاعة
So many organizations these days are keen on designing beautiful workplaces
الكثير من المؤوسسات هذه الأيام مهتمة لتصميم مكان عمل جميل جذاب
that look like anything but work:
يبدو مثل أي شي بعيداً عن العمل
vacation resorts, coffee shops, playgrounds or college campuses --
منتجعات سياحية , مقاهي , ملاعب أو مدن جامعية
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Based on the promises of positive psychology,
بناء على وعود علم النفس الإيجابي
we speak of play and gamification,
نتحدث عن اللعب و التعليب
and one start-up even says that when someone gets fired,
واحدى الشركات القائمة تصرح بأن الذي يتم طرده
they have graduated.
هو تم تخريجه
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
That kind of beautiful language only goes "skin deep,
هذا النوع من اللغة الجميلة يدخل في الأعماق
but ugly cuts clean to the bone,"
لكن البشاعة تقطع العظام
as the writer Dorothy Parker once put it.
كما قالت الكاتبة دورثي باركر
To be authentic is to be ugly.
أن تكون حقيقي هي أن تكون بشعاً
It doesn't mean that you can't have fun or must give in to the vulgar or cynical,
هذا لا يعني إنه لا يكمن أن تستمتع
but it does mean that you speak the actual ugly truth.
بل تعني أن تتحدث بالحقيقة القبيحة
Like this manufacturer
مثل هذا المصنع
that wanted to transform one of its struggling business units.
الذي أراد أن يحول أحدى وحدات التجارية العالقة
It identified, named and pinned on large boards all the issues --
قد قاموا بالتعرف و تسمية و تحديد كل المشاكل على لوحات كبيرة
and there were hundreds of them --
و كان هناك المئات منهم
that had become obstacles to better performance.
أصبحت عقبات في طريق الإنتاج الأفضل
They put them on boards, moved them all into one room,
و وضعوهم جميعا في لوحة و نقلوهم جميعا في نفس الغرفة
which they called "the ugly room."
و سموها الغرفة القبيحة
The ugly became visible for everyone to see --
القبيح أصبح ظاهر للجميع
it was celebrated.
تم الاحتفال به
And the ugly room served as a mix of mirror exhibition and operating room --
و الغرف القبيحة تخدم لخلط المرايا
a biopsy on the living flesh to cut out all the bureaucracy.
عينة من النسيج الحي لكي يتم استئصال كل الروتين
The ugliest part of our body is our brain.
أقبح جزء من جسمنا هو عقلنا
Literally and neurologically.
حرفياً و من الناحية العصبية
Our brain renders ugly what is unfamiliar ...
عقولنا تقوم بتسمية القبح ما هو غير مألوف
modern art, atonal music,
الفن الحديث الموسيقا اللامقامية
jazz, maybe --
الجاز،ربما
VR goggles for that matter --
نظارات محاكات الواقع
strange objects, sounds and people.
أشكال غربية ، أصوات و أشخاص
But we've all been ugly once.
و لكن كلنا كنا قبيحين في مرة
We were a weird-looking baby,
كنا أطفال غريبين
a new kid on the block, a foreigner.
طفل جديد في الحي ، أجنبي
And we will be ugly again when we don't belong.
و سوف نكون قبيحين مجددا في مكان لا ننتمي اليه
The Center for Political Beauty,
مركز الجمال السياسي
an activist collective in Berlin,
تجمع نشطاء في برلين
recently staged an extreme artistic intervention.
مؤخرا قاموا بوقفه صارمه بخصوص الفن
With the permission of relatives,
بعد أذن المعنين بالأمر
it exhumed the corpses of refugees who had drowned at Europe's borders,
لقد قاموا باستخراج بقايا جثث اللاجئين الذين غرقوا في الحدود الاوروبية
transported them all the way to Berlin,
تنقلوا بهم في شوارع برلين
and then reburied them at the heart of the German capital.
و دفنوهم في قلب عاصمة المانيا
The idea was to allow them to reach their desired destination,
الفكرة هي كانت أن يوصلوهم إلى هدفهم
if only after their death.
حتى لو من بعد موتهم
Such acts of beautification may not be pretty,
مثل هذا الافعال من التجميل قد لا تكون جميلة
but they are much needed.
لكنها مطلوبة
Because things tend to get ugly when there's only one meaning, one truth,
لأن الأشياء تصبح قبيحة عندما يكون لها معنى واحد، حقيقة واحدة
only answers and no questions.
فقط اسئلة، و لا أجوبة
Beautiful organizations keep asking questions.
المؤسسات الجميلة تظل تسأل إسئلة
They remain incomplete,
تظل غير مكتمله
which is the fourth and the last of the principles.
و هو المبدأ الرابع و الأخير.
[Remain Incomplete]
(تظل غير مكتمله)
Recently I was in Paris,
مؤخرا كنت في باريس
and a friend of mine took me to Nuit Debout,
و صديق لي اخذني إلى مقر حركه نوتي ديبيوت
which stands for "up all night,"
و هي حركه تؤمن بالسهر
the self-organized protest movement
و هي حركه تظاهريه منظمه
that had formed in response to the proposed labor laws in France.
و تكونت كرد فعل لمقترح قانون العمل في فرنسا
Every night, hundreds gathered at the Place de la République.
كل ليله يجتمع المئات في قصر الجمهورية
Every night they set up a small, temporary village
في كل ليله يبنون قريه صغيرة مؤقته
to deliberate their own vision of the French Republic.
لكي يعرضوا تصورهم للجمهوريه الفرنسيه
And at the core of this adhocracy
و في داخل هذه المنظمه المرنة
was a general assembly where anybody could speak
يكون هناك تجمع عام يمكن لأي شخص أن يتحدث فيه
using a specially designed sign language.
باستخدام لغه إشاره معينه
Like Occupy Wall Street and other protest movements,
مثل منظمات و حركات تظاهريه أخرى
Nuit Debout was born in the face of crisis.
نوتي ديبيوت ولدت في وجه أزمه
It was messy --
كانت هناك فوضى
full of controversies and contradictions.
مليئه بالاختلاف في الاراء و التناقضات
But whether you agreed with the movement's goals or not,
و سواء اتفقت مع أهداف الحركه ام لا
every gathering was a beautiful lesson in raw humanity.
كل تجمع كان درسا في الإنسانية الخالصة
And how fitting that Paris --
و قابلية باريس على التقبل
the city of ideals, the city of beauty --
مدينه الأفكار و مدينه الجمال
was it's stage.
كيف تم عرضه
It reminds us that like great cities,
لقد ذكرنا بأن المدن الكبيره،
the most beautiful organizations are ideas worth fighting for --
أن معظم المؤسسات الجميله هي أفكار يجب المحاربة من أجلها
even and especially when their outcome is uncertain.
حتى و خصوصا عندما يكون ناتجها غير محدد
They are movements;
هي حركات ؛
they are always imperfect, never fully organized,
دائما ما تكون غير كامله و غير منظمه
so they avoid ever becoming banal.
لكي تتجنب أن تكون رتيبة
They have something but we don't know what it is.
لديها شي و لكن نحن لا نعرف ما هو
They remain mysterious; we can't take our eyes off them.
تظل غامضه و لا يمكننا أن نرفع أعيننا عنها
We find them beautiful.
نجدها جميله.
So to do the unnecessary,
اذا لكي نفعل الغير ضروري
to create intimacy,
لنخلق الود
to be ugly,
لكي نكون قبحاء
to remain incomplete --
لكي نظل غير مكتملين
these are not only the qualities of beautiful organizations,
هذه ليست فقط مميزات المؤسسات الجميلة
these are inherently human characteristics.
ولكنها صفات بشريه متوارثه
And these are also the qualities of what we call home.
و هي ايضا صفات موجوده في ما نسميه المنزل
And as we disrupt, and are disrupted,
و عندما نكون مشوشين و نشوش
the least we can do is to ensure
أقل ما يمكن فعله لضمان
that we still feel at home in our organizations,
أننا موجودون في منزلنا عندما نكون في مؤسساتنا
and that we use our organizations to create that feeling for others.
و نستخدم منظماتنا لكي نشعر الاخرين بذلك
Beauty can save the world when we embrace these principles
الجمال يمكن أن ينقذ العالم عندما نحتضن هذه المبادىء
and design for them.
و نصمم من أجلها
In the face of artificial intelligence and machine learning,
في وجه الذكاء الاصطناعي
we need a new radical humanism.
نحتاج إلى بشر بجذور جديدة
We must acquire and promote a new aesthetic and sentimental education.
لابد لنا أن نكتسب و نروج لتعليم جديد جمالي و خالد
Because if we don't,
لأنه أن لم نفعل
we might end up feeling like aliens
سوف نشعر بأننا غرباء
in organizations and societies that are full of smart machines
في مؤسسات و مجتمعات مليئة بالالات الذكية
that have no appreciation whatsoever
لا يوجد فيها أي تقدير أبدا
for the unnecessary,
الغير الضروري
the intimate,
الود
the incomplete
الغير كامل
and definitely not for the ugly.
و قطعاً ليس للقبيح
Thank you.
شكراً.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)